Davidson, Richard C.; Collection apap398
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Richard C. Davidson Collection
1937-1960
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap398
0.8 cubic ft.
This collection includes the by-laws and regulations, correspondence, meeting minutes, and other administrative records and records of the political activities of The Sentinel Rifle and Revolver Club of New York from the late 1930s to 1960.
Content Description
This collection documents the records of The Sentinel Rifle and Revolver Club which Richard Davidson helped found and later served as Club Secretary. This includes business, executive committee, and regular club meeting minutes and other related documents; intraclub bulletins and communications; business materials; by-laws; correspondence with government officials; magazines, newspapers, and other firearm-related organization materials on firearms legislation at the local, state, and federal levels; materials from the Club's marksman training school; National Rifle Association materials; range rules and regulations; interclub competition records; competition patches; and Club certificates.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically. There are no series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Denise Davidson donated all materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2022 and 2024.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Biographical Note
Born in Yonkers, New York, Richard C. Davidson (1917-2004) was the oldest of three children born to Charles Davidson and Zara Odell. After graduating from New York University with a degree in Business Administration, he lived in Yonkers and worked in Manhattan for much of his life, except when he served in the Army Air Force during World War II. He was married twice, first to Violet Pascotta with whom he had no children and whom he divorced in 1963. Shortly afterward, Davidson married Marguerite Melanson with whom he had one child, Denise Davidson. They moved to New Jersey in 1968, eventually buying a home in Ridgefield Park, where he lived until his death. When he retired in 1983, he had been working for McLean Trucking Company for nearly 30 years. At retirement, Davidson's title was Market Manager for Textiles.
In the late 1930s, Davidson and some close friends, including his brother-in-law William Lenau, founded The Sentinel Rifle and Revolver Club that became affiliated with the National Rifle Association (NRA). In addition to conducting target practice and participating in shooting competitions, they went on annual deer-hunting trips in Upstate New York. They were also politically engaged with regard to the issue of gun rights, lobbying against limitations to the right to bear arms. Soon after World War II began in Europe, Davidson participated in a nationwide effort to re-arm the British public whose arms had been confiscated by the British government. Thousands of guns were collected and shipped to England in 1940 in the context of a feared German invasion. A lifetime member of the NRA, Davidson remained a passionate defender of the Second Amendment throughout his life.
Davidson, Richard C. (1917-2004); Sentinel Rifle and Revolver Club; Firearms ownership--New York (State)--History; Shooting--New York (State)--History; Hunting--New York (State)--History; Minutes (administrative records); Newspaper clippings; Correspondence
- Range Rules and Regulations, 1937; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General Correspondence, 1937-1938; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Business, 1937; 1939-1940; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General Club Communication, 1937; 1939-1941; 1943; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Firearms Legislation, 1937; 1940-1942; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- National Rifle Association Membership Certificate, 1939 (Map-tube 1)
- Headings and Seals, 1939; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Meetings, 1939-1941; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- By-Laws, 1939; 1944; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Competition Patches, 1939; 1947-1948; Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Certificate of Incorporation, 1940 (Map-tube 1)
- Inter-Club Competition, 1940-1941; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Club Certification, 1940; 1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, 1941-1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- School Inquiries, 1942-1943; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- School Business, 1943; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Business Meetings, 1944-1947; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Firearms Legislation, 1946-1952; 1957-1958; 1960; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Associated Council on Firearms, 1953-1957; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)